舰长，我们已经抵达3号转向点
We have reached projected point 3, captain.
设定新航道，方位201坐标15
Adjust to new course 2-0-1 mark 1-5.
谢谢，史波克先生
Thank you, Mr. Spock.
吉姆
Jim.
- 医生，她情况怎么样了？ - 不大好
- How is she, doctor? - No change.
真得感谢星际舰队！
Small thanks to the Starfleet.
协调员，这事儿怪不得星际舰队
Now really, commissioner, you can't blame the Starfleet.
我本来应该提前接种防疫
I should have received the proper inoculations ahead of time.
樱花病是一种极其罕见的病
Sakuro's disease is extremely rare.
感染这种病的机率差不多是十亿分之一
The chances of anyone contracting it are literally billions to one.
大夫，我被派往埃普西隆卡纳瑞三号阻止战争冲突
I was sent to Epsilon Canaris III to prevent a war, doctor.
托星际舰队医疗分部行事拖沓的福
Thanks to the inefficiency of the medical branch of the Starfleet,
在工作完全做好之前我就被迫提早回程
I've been forced to leave before my job was done.
协调员，我向你保证，一旦我们回到进取号
Commissioner, I assure you that once we reach the Enterprise
使用她先进的医疗设备，我们绝对能够
with its medical facilities, we'll have you back to your job
使你尽快返回你的工作
in time for you to prevent that war.
舰长，我们什么时候才能到你的飞船呢？
How soon will we rendezvous with that ship of yours, captain?
协调员，只需要4小时21分钟
In exactly four hours, 21 minutes, commissioner.
- 舰长 - 嗯？
- Captain. - Yes.
你看一下自动扫描仪
Will you check your automatic scanner, please?
这是什么？我以前从来没有见过
That's odd. I've never seen anything like that before.
我也是
Nor have I.
它正以曲速向我们飞来
Heading directly toward us at warp speed.
它好像故意堵在我们的航道上 史波克先生，扫描器读数？
It's staying right with us. Sensor readings, Mr. Spock.
好像是由一团氢离子构成的云层
Vaguely like a cloud of ionized hydrogen,
但是发出强烈的电磁脉冲
but with strong erratic electrical impulses.
我们撞上它了
We've got it.
- 舰长，方向舵不听使唤了 - 太空梭失去控制了
- Helm does not answer, captain. - Neither do the pods.
与外界的通讯中断，电路超载，切断所有电力中继
Communications are dead. Building overload. Cut all power relays.
已切断，舰长
Cut, captain.
舰长，到底怎么了，快告诉我！
Captain, what's happening? I demand to know.
哈特福德女士，我们知道的不比你多
You already know as much as we do, Miss Hedford.
不管外面是个什么东西
Whatever that thing is outside,
总之它使我们偏离了既定航道
it yanked us off course from the Enterprise.
我们现在的方位是98坐标12，直冲伽马卡纳瑞区域
Now on course 9-8 mark 1-2, heading directly toward Gamma Canaris region.
吉姆，我们必须把哈特福德女士带回进取号！她的病情
Jim. We've got to get Miss Hedford back to the Enterprise. Her condition.
我知道，老骨头，但是现在只能听天由命
I know, Bones. But there's nothing I can do about it.
你们必须马上返回与进取号会合的航道上！
Then I insist you make your scheduled rendezvous with the Enterprise.
哈特福德女士，我们已尽力
Miss Hedford, we'll do what we can when we can.
目前这种情况，我们孤立无援
At the moment, we're helpless. You might as well sit back...
你也只能好好坐稳而已
...and enjoy the ride.
宇宙，终极的边疆
Space, the final frontier.
这是星舰进取号的航程
These are the voyages of the starship Enterprise.
它的五年任务，是去探索未知的新世界
Its five-year mission: To explore strange new worlds,
去发现新的世界和新的文明
to seek out new life and new civilisations,
勇敢的航向前人未至之境
to boldly go where no man has gone before.
【星际迷航：原初】
-=THE LAST FANTASY=-
荣誉出品
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业途径
-=TLF字幕组=-
翻译：多宝大如来
校对：喜马拉雅
第二季第九集
「变形生物」
进取号，这里是伽利略号太空梭，请回话
Enterprise, this is the Galileo. Come in, please. Come in.
Enterprise, this is the Galileo. Come in, please.
情况不妙
No good.
信号根本发不出去，老骨头?
We're not transmitting. Bones?
氮氧环境，还有少许氪，氩，氖等等
Oxygen-nitrogen atmosphere, some krypton, argon, neon.
温度为华氏75度
Temperature, 75 degrees Fahrenheit.
几乎完全等同于地球的大气环境
Practically identical to Earth's atmosphere.
- 史波克？ - 重力和地球一样
- Spock? - Gravity similar to Earth.
根据星球的体积，这种重力很不寻常
Most unusual, in view of its size.
星球的主体部分主要由铁元素和镍元素组成
The bulk of the body seems to be iron and nickel.
比起陨星来更接近小行星
More than an asteroid, like a small planetoid, I should say,
有可能是一颗行星解体后的碎片
possibly a remnant from a planet breakup.
完全适合人类生命
Totally suitable for human life.
好吧，咱们出去瞧瞧，把相位枪准备好
All right, we get out and get under. Issue phasers.
老骨头，保持高度警惕
Bones, maintain full alert.
协调员，您先在这里休息一会儿
Commissioner, if you'll stay inside.
舰长，我应该休息多久呢？
Just how long am I supposed to stay inside, captain?
好问题！我也不知道
That's a very good question. I wish I could answer it.
好，走吧
All right. Let's go.
老骨头，四处探查一下
Take a look around, Bones.
太不寻常了
Most unusual.
不太可能
Unlikely.
舰长，我得说极其不可能
In fact, captain, I would say quite impossible.
- 机器没有任何故障但就是不工作 - 没错
- Nothing wrong and nothing works. - Precisely.
- 肯定有什么原因 - 没错
- There must be a reason. - Obviously.
再好好检查一下
Let's look a little further.
吉姆，我刚刚用三录仪扫描了一下周边环境
Jim, I just took a tricorder sweep, and I got the exact same readings
读数和太空梭刚偏离航道时的读数几乎一样
almost as Spock got when we were pulled off course.
- 离子云？ - 我觉得是
- The ionized cloud? - I think so.
只是这次离子云读数在星球表面，就在那边
Only it reads here on the surface with us. It's off in that direction.
而且读数显示其不是固体，非常不稳定
And it doesn't read solid. It's more unstable.
像是一团稀薄的气体
Tenuous, like a collection of gases.
你们好！
Hello!
有趣
Fascinating.
老骨头，读取一下那人的生理信息
Bones, get a physiological reading on that, whatever it is.
你们好！
Hello!
你们是真实的吗？
Are you real?
我的意思是，你们不是我幻想出来的吧
I mean, I'm not imagining you, am I?
绝对真实
We're real enough.
你会讲英语？是地球人吗？
You speak English. Earth people?
我们来自星际联邦
From the Federation.
星际
The F...
好吧，管他呢，我叫寇可兰
Well, it doesn't matter. I'm Cochrane.
我也不知道我被困在这里待了多久了
I've been marooned here who knows how long.
见到你们我实在太高兴了
If you only knew how good it is to see you.
见到女人我更高兴
And a woman.
而且还是一个大美女
A beautiful one at that.
我是进取号舰长詹姆士·寇克
I'm Captain James T. Kirk, commanding the starship Enterprise.
这位是我的大副史波克
This is my first officer, Mr. Spock.
- 你是瓦肯人吧？ - 是的
- You're a Vulcan, aren't you? - Correct.
首席医官伦纳得·麦考伊
Chief Surgeon Leonard McCoy.
- 大夫 - 幸会
- Doctor. - Pleasure.
星联助理委员哈特福德
And excuse me, Assistant Federation Commissioner Hedford.
女士
Ma'am.
真是雪中送炭
Food to a starving man.
你们都是我的炭火
All of you.
嘿，这艘船真不错
Hey, that's a nice ship.
看起来风格简约又干净
Simple and clean.
打算修好它吗？
Been trying to get her to go again?
我看还是省省吧
Forget it. It won't work.
他的各项生理读数都说他是一个地球人，吉姆
He's human, Jim. Everything checks out perfectly.
寇可兰先生
Mr. Cochrane.
我们是被一股神秘的力量强行
We were forced off our course...
拖离航道到这里来的
...and taken here by some force we couldn't identify.
这股力量我们无法分析，所以不知道来自何方
Which seems to be on the surface of this body at the moment.
我也不清楚
I wouldn't know anything about that.
你刚刚说我们无法使这艘太空梭再度运行吗?
You say we'll be unable to get the ship to function again?
绝对不行 这里有某种阻尼场
Not a chance. There's some sort of damping field down here.
动力系统都无法工作，相信我吧
Power systems don't work. Take my word for it.
我们会继续尝试
You don't mind if we continue to try.
当然可以，随你便，反正你们有的是时间
Go right ahead. You've got plenty of time.
寇可兰先生，谈谈你的情况吧
What about you, Cochrane?
你是怎么到这儿来的呢？
How did you get here?
我刚不是说了吗，落难在此
Marooned. I told you.
咱们要是想聊天的话有的是时间
Look, we'll have lots of time to learn about each other.
我的小屋就在那个方向上，一起去坐坐吧
I have a small place over that way. All the comforts of home.
你们可以洗个热水澡
I can even offer you a hot bath.
真有眼力，我很想马上就洗
How perceptive of you to notice that I needed one.
寇可兰先生，您说得实在太笼统
If you don't mind, Mr. Cochrane, I'd like a little more than just a statement
这里离航路很远
that you were marooned here.
您是怎么落难的？
It's a long way off the beaten path.
说得对，所以我看见你们才这么高兴
That's right. That's why I'm so glad to see you.
我会告诉你们一切，但是这儿说话不方便
Look, I'll tell you everything you want to know. But not here.
- 你们的太空船真是太漂亮了 - 那是自然
- Your ship is sure a beauty. - Yes, she is.
而且你现在也已经闭锁了一段时间了
And you've been out of circulation quite a while.
很多原理你可能以前从来没有听说过，史波克先生
The principles may be new to you. Mr. Spock...
给寇可兰先生讲解一下推动器工作原理吧
...why don't you explain our methods of propulsion to Mr. Cochrane?
他虽然话多，但是有用的说得不多
He talks a lot, but he doesn't say much.
- 而且我还注意到一些其他东西 - 是什么？
- I've noticed something else. - What's that?
- 他看上去很面熟 - 面熟？
- He looks familiar. - Familiar?
经你这么一说，我也觉得
Now that you mention it, he does.
我一时想不起来在哪里见过他，但是
I can't quite place him, but...
哈特福德女士的情况怎么样？
What about Miss Hedford?
目前还没发烧
No temperature yet.
但是事情耽搁不得，吉姆
But we've got to get underway soon, Jim.
我敢保证她马上就会有严重的症状了
I guarantee you it will develop.
到那时我们该怎么办？
What are we going to do?
先去寇可兰那坐坐吧
Take Cochrane up on his offer.
寇可兰先生，你自己建的这个？
You built this, Mr. Cochrane?
没错，我的小船坠毁前装着必要的工具和材料
Yes. I had tools and supplies left over from my crash.
还不赖，虽说不如地球上的舒服，但起码能住
It's not bad. Not Earth, of course, but it's liveable.
我在那边的小山丘上种植了一些蔬菜
I grow vegetables in the fields over that next ridge.
进来吧
Come on in.
简直就像家那样舒适
All the comforts of home, indeed, Mr. Cochrane.
你从哪弄的这些老古董？
Where did you get the antiques?
你是说这些仪器？
You mean my instruments?
我猜外面的世界一定变化了很多吧
I imagine things have changed a lot since I crashed.
其实变化也不算太大
Not that much.
你这里怎么这么热？
Must you keep it so terribly hot in here?
温度一直保持在华氏72度
The temperature is a constant 72 degrees.
喝点冷饮吧
Let me get you something cool to drink.
你觉得很热吗？
Do you feel hot?
我觉得心里有火，无处宣泄！
I feel infuriated, deeply put upon, and absolutely outraged.
走这么久你肯定累了，先休息一会儿吧
It was quite a hike here. You're tired. Just take it easy for a while.
我一会儿就休息
I'll rest later, doctor.
她已经开始出现症状了，感觉热是第一个征兆
Temperature, captain. First sign.
我知道我们时间不多了
Yes, I know. It means we're running out of time.
舰长，医生
Captain. Doctor.
那是什么？
What was that?
有时候光线会造成奇特的光影效果
Sometimes the light plays tricks on you.
我有时候在光线的刺激下也会产生幻觉
You'd be surprised what I've imagined I've seen around here sometimes.
寇可兰先生，那绝不是幻觉
We imagined nothing, Mr. Cochrane.
有个实实在在存在的东西，刚刚就在外边
There was an entity out there,
我怀疑刚才那怪光和把我们带到这里的 离子云有联系
and I suspect it was the same entity which brought us here.
请解释一下
Please explain.
没什么可说的
There's nothing to explain.
谢谢
Thank you.
我告诉你，当我的船员切身安全受到威胁
You'll find I have a very low tolerance level
我的脾气是很不好的！
where the safety of my people are concerned.
你独自一人生活在这个荒无人烟的地方 而且拒绝透露有用的信息！
We find you here where no human has any business being.
我们突然在太空中遇险最后流落到这么个地方！
We were virtually hijacked in space and brought here.
我现在不是请求你给我们一个解释
I'm not just requesting an explanation, mister.
我在要求一个解释！
I'm demanding one.
好吧
All right.
- 它叫做“伴随实体” - 什么？
- It was the Companion. - The what?
这是我给它取的名字
That's what I call it.
实际上我的船并非坠毁于此
As a matter of fact, captain, I didn't crash here.
我是被带到这里的
I was brought here in my disabled ship.
当时我已经奄奄一息了，“伴随实体”救了我的命
I was almost dead. The Companion saved my life.
你当时受伤了？
You were injured?
史波克先生，我当时奄奄一息
I was dying, Mr. Spock.
你现在看起来很健康，怎么回事？
You seem perfectly all right now. What was the matter?
那时我已经是个老头子了
I was an old man.
什么？
You were what?
我也不清楚是怎么回事，但是“伴随者”把我返老还童了
I don't know how it did it, but the Companion rejuvenated me,
我从一个老头子又变成了一个小伙子
made me young again, like I am now.
我对你的这个故事持保留意见
I prefer to reserve judgement on that part of your story, sir.
同时，你能不能给我解释一下
Meanwhile, would you please explain
你的这个伴随者到底是什么东西？
exactly what this Companion of yours is?
我跟你说过了，我也不知道，它存在
I told you, I don't know what it is. It exists,
它是生命体，而且我还能跟它交流
it lives, and I can communicate with it.
- 这可真是一个奇异的故事 - 寇可兰先生
- That's a pretty far-out story. - Mr. Cochrane...
你的名是什么？ - 杰佛瑞
...do you have a first name? - Zefram.
杰佛瑞·寇可兰
Zefram Cochrane...
来自半人马三星？
...of Alpha Centauri?
- 曲速引擎的发明者？ - 没错，舰长
- The discoverer of the space warp? - That's right, captain.
这绝对不可能！
But that's impossible.
杰佛瑞·寇可兰150年前就去世了！
Zefram Cochrane died 150 years ago.
杰佛瑞·寇可兰的名号响彻寰宇
The name of Zefram Cochrane is revered throughout the galaxy.
有好多星球以他的名字命名，还有很多大学，城市等等
Planets were named after him, great universities, cities.
寇可兰先生，您的故事着实不太可信
Isn't your story a little improbable, Mr. Cochrane?
我说的都是真的，我来到这里的时候已经87岁了
No, it's true. I was 87 years old when I came here.
你说这个伴随者发现了你并且还让你返老还童
You say this Companion found you and rejuvenated you.
你87岁的时候为什么还在太空里旅行？
What were you doing in space at the age of 87?
我当时身心俱疲
I was tired, captain.
行将枯朽，我想死在太空里
I was going to die, and I wanted to die in space. That's all.
确实，他的尸体从来没有被找到过
True, his body was never found.
史波克先生，活生生的就站在你面前
You're looking at it, Mr. Spock.
果真如此，你的生理年龄被缩减了好多
If so, you wear your age very well.
- 你感觉怎么样了？ - 你说呢？我难受死了
- How do you feel? - Terrible. How should I feel?
你现在有点发烧，最好躺下休息
You're running a little temperature. Perhaps you should lie down.
医生，麻烦你离我远点，因为实在是太热了
Doctor, will you please just leave me alone? It's the heat.
好的，尽量放松身心
All right. Try to relax.
吉姆
Jim.
现在开始有症状了，是发烧
It's started, the fever.
已经超过100华氏度了，而且还在上升
It's over 100, and it's climbing.
还有多久？
How long do we have?
最多能挺几个小时
A matter of hours, that's all.
寇可兰先生，您说您在150年前就来到这里了
Mr. Cochrane, you say you were brought here 150 years ago.
可是我看您顶多35岁
You don't look a day over 35.
伴随者让我返老还童，并且一直保持 35岁的生理年龄
I haven't aged. The Companion sees to that.
舰长
Captain.
这些设备，确实属于寇可兰的那个年代
These instruments, they date from the time indicated.
都是你船上的吗，寇可兰先生？
From your ship, Mr. Cochrane?
都是我从船上拆下来的
I cannibalized it.
除了这些设备，我其他的生活需求 比如食物，水，花园
The food, water, gardens, everything else I need,
都是伴随者使用周围的物质给我创造的
the Companion gives me. Apparently creates it out of the native elements.
您说您能跟它交流
You say you can communicate with it.
那您不妨问问它干嘛把我们带到这里来
Perhaps you can find out what we're doing here.
- 我已经知道了 - 那您不打算告诉我们吗？
- I already know. - You wouldn't mind telling us?
- 我怕说了你不高兴 - 我已经很不高兴了！
- You won't like it. - I already don't like it.
你们来这里的主要目的就是做我的伙伴
You're here to keep me company.
你的意思是其实是你把我们带到这里来的？
You mean you brought us here?
不，是伴随者带你们过来的
No, the Companion did.
我跟伴随者说如果这样下去我会孤独至死
I told it I'd die of loneliness.
我本以为这样它就会放了我
I thought it would release me.
结果它把你们带到这里来了
Instead, it brought you here.
不！
No!
不！不！
No! No!
好恶心
That's disgusting.
我们又不是禽兽！
We're not animals.
不
No.
简直是奇耻大辱！
No, it's inhuman. No.
史波克，使用三录仪收集更多的信息
Spock, run additional tricorder readings.
尽全力分析，争取能发明一种战胜它的武器
Learn anything you can. Find me a weapon to use against this thing.
武器？你想让我消灭它吗？
You ask me to find a weapon. Do you intend to destroy it?
如果只有这样才能离开这个星球的话，是的
I intend to do whatever is necessary to get us off this planet
况且哈特福德女士的病也耽搁不得
and Commissioner Hedford to the hospital.
要是伴随者挡路，那咱们就把它赶走
If the Companion stands in the way, then we push it out of the way.
明白了，史波克？
Clear, Spock?
舰长，明白了
Quite clear, captain.
好，忙你的去吧
Very well. You have your orders.
寇可兰先生，离开这儿会对你有影响吗？
Mr. Cochrane, if you left here, what would happen to you?
我的身体会重新进入正常老化
I'd begin to age again, normally.
那你想离开这里吗？
Do you want to leave here?
舰长，你相信我，永生实在是太无聊了
Believe me, captain, immortality consists largely of boredom.
外面的银河系世界是什么样子的？
What's it like out there, in the galaxy?
我们已经探索的星球约有1000颗！
We're on 1,000 planets and spreading out.
我们的星舰飞跃了你无法想象的距离
We cross fantastic distances
生命在银河系中遍地开花！
and everything's alive, Cochrane.
我们估计有上百万颗星球都有智慧生物生存！
Life everywhere. We estimate there are millions of planets with intelligent life.
这些星球都在那里等着我们去探索！如何？
We haven't begun to map them. Interesting?
你觉得一颗已经沉睡了150年的心灵
How would you like to go to sleep for 150 years
突然苏醒在一个崭新的世界会怎么样？
and wake up in a new world?
那些未知的新世界在那里等你去探索
It's all out there waiting for you.
但我们需要你的帮助才能离开这里
But we'll need your help to get away.
我决定帮你们！
You've got it.
这个伴随者能够使用周围的元素制造出物体
You seem to think this Companion of yours can do almost anything.
它确实有这个能耐
I said it was very powerful.
- 那它能治好这位女士吗？ - 这我不清楚
- Could it cure her? - I don't know.
你是如何跟它交流的？
How do you communicate with it?
我们的交流类似于心电感应，属于非语言层面
It's on a non-verbal level, but I usually get my message across.
我们必须尝试跟它交流，这方面我们必须依靠你
We've got to try. We're helpless. See if it can do something.
你是怎么跟他交流的？
How do you do it?
首先我要排除杂念，然后它自然会过来
I just sort of clear my mind, and it comes.
老骨头，发表一下看法
Bones, what do you make of that?
像是某种共生关系
Almost a symbiosis of some kind.
- 一种交和 - 我也是这么想的
- A sort of joining. - Exactly what I think.
我觉得二者的关系并不是主人和
Not exactly like a pet owner
宠物之间那样简单，你觉得呢？
speaking to a beloved animal, would you say?
- 绝对不止如此 - 我同意
- No, it's more than that. - Agreed.
更像是
More like...
爱情
...love.
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
稍微有点消耗体力，不过没什么大碍
Yes, it kind of drains me a little, but I'm all right.
我们的事儿它答应吗？
Well?
伴随者也无能为力
The Companion can't do anything to help Miss Hedford.
那哈特福德女士必死无疑
Then she'll die.
要是我有办法，一定全力以赴去帮忙
If there's anything I could do to help, I would, and I will.
但是伴随者是指望不上了
But we can expect nothing from the Companion.
史波克！
Spock!
- 你没事吧？ - 大夫先生，我没事
- Are you all right? - Yes. Quite all right, doctor.
发生了一件很有趣的事情
A most fascinating thing happened.
很明显，伴随者将一种原始的
Apparently, the Companion imparted to me
高压电流
a rather quaint, old-fashioned electric shock...
输入到我的身体里
...of respectable voltage.
- 你的意思是它袭击你了？ - 显而易见
- It attacked you? - Evidently.
由此可知，它的身体中有一大部分
Unquestionably, a large part of its substance...
组织就是电流
...is simple electricity.
哦，我明白了
Oh, yes.
史波克先生，虽说我不是科学家或物理学家
I'm not a scientist or a physicist, Mr. Spock,
但是我知道任何能够产生电流的东西
but am I correct in assuming that anything that generates electricity
都能够短路
can be shorted out?
医生，你说得很对
Quite correct, doctor.
把这个仪器放在伴随者附近
Put this in the proximity of the Companion.
只要按下这个开关
Throw this switch,
它就能够扰乱那个生物所制造的电流回路
and it will scramble every electrical impulse the creature can produce.
绝对错不了
It cannot fail.
寇可兰，怎么了？
It troubles you, Cochrane?
伴随者救了我的命
The Companion saved my life.
这么些年来是它一直照顾我
It's taken care of me all these years.
我们之间的关系
We've been...
怎么说呢？非常亲密
...very close in a way that's hard to explain.
我甚至对它有点难以启齿的依恋
I suppose I even have a sort of affection for it.
可是它同样也是囚禁你的罪魁祸首
It's also keeping you prisoner.
反正我不希望它被杀
I don't want it killed.
我们只是暂时把它瘫痪而已
We may simply render it powerless.
可是你怎么保证呢？ 你有可能会杀掉它
But you don't know. You could kill it.
柯克，这一点我绝无法容忍
I won't stand for that, Kirk.
寇可兰先生，我们需要离开这里
We're getting out of here, Cochrane.
请面对现实！
Face up to it.
我会不择手段地确保我手下人的生命安全！
I'll do anything I have to to save all of our lives.
站在你的立场上讲，你确实没错
I suppose, from your point of view, you're right.
寇可兰先生，我们能够理解你的感受
We understand how you feel, Mr. Cochrane.
可是眼下我们别无它法
But it has to be done.
好吧，要我出去引它出来吗？
All right. Do you want me to contact it?
请一定帮忙
Please. Outside.
有句俗话怎么说来着？
What was it they used to call it?
舍不得孩子套不着狼？
The Judas goat?
舰长，确实有一定危险
There is some risk, captain.
我们尚不清楚伴随者的能量究竟有多大
We do not know the extent of its powers.
它也不知道我们的
Nor it ours.
开始
Now.
停止！你想杀了他们吗？
Stop it! You're killing them!
求你了，请停止，他们没法呼吸了！
Stop it, please! Stop it! You're choking them!
放了他们吧
Let them go!
他们快憋死了！
You're choking them!
别这样！
Stop it!
- 吉姆，你还好吧？ - 还好
- Are you all right, Jim? - Yeah.
- 史波克？ - 我没事
- Spock? - Fine.
寇可兰把它引过去了
Cochrane got it off of us.
但是我不知道这对我们算是好事还是坏事
But I don't know whether he did us a favour or not.
你说这话是什么意思？
What kind of talk is that?
我们怎么能斗得过那东西呢？
How do you fight a thing like that?
做为一船之长
I've got a ship up there somewhere,
我要为这里的四个性命负责
the responsibility of four lives down here,
现在他们中的一个因为我的缘故就要死掉了
one of them dying because of me.
这不是你的错
It isn't your fault.
老骨头，我是舰长，舰长就是扛事儿的
I'm in command, Bones. It makes it my fault.
我们怎么能斗得过那样一个生命体呢？
How do you fight a thing like that?
别忘了，武力从来就不是解决问题的首选
Maybe you're a soldier so often
你不仅要学会做战士，更要懂得沟通
that you forget you're also trained to be a diplomat.
当大棒不顶用的时候，干嘛不试试胡罗卜？
Why not try a carrot instead of a stick?
- 史波克 - 舰长，什么事？
- Spock. - Yes, captain?
咱们的穿梭机里有宇宙翻译器
The universal translator on the shuttlecraft.
咱们试试用那玩意儿和那个生物体沟通一下
We can try that, talk to that thing.
宇宙翻译器不是为这种生命形式设计的
The translator is for use with more congruent life forms.
看看能不能调整一下，尝试和那个东西沟通
Adjust it. Change it. The trouble with immortality is it's boring.
况且还可以消磨这里无限的时间
Adjusting it will give you something to do.
如果我有办法拓宽它的接收模式的话是有可能的
It is possible. If I could widen its pattern of reception.
这项工作刚好能发挥你的天才，干吧史波克
Right down your alley, Spock. Get it here and get to work.
那个生物还在外面，你最好走那边
And that thing is still out there. Better go that way.
- 情况怎么样了？ - 更糟了
- Any change? - Yes. For the worse.
星舰日志，星历3219.8.
Ship's log, stardate 3219. 8.
史考特少校于舰长不在舰时
Lieutenant Commander Scott
代理寇克舰长进行记录
recording in the absence of Captain Kirk.
载有寇克舰长
A shuttlecraft, bearing the captain,
大副，首席医官麦考伊
the first officer, Chief Surgeon McCoy,
星联助理协调员哈特福德女士的太空梭
and Assistant Federation Commissioner Hedford,
没能按计划时间与进取号会合
is now definitely overdue for a rendezvous with the Enterprise.
我们目前正在尝试搜索
We are attempting to backtrack it.
史考特先生
Mr. Scott.
计算机中心报告说我们马上就要到达
Computer central reports that we are coming up on the coordinates
太空梭失踪之前的最后一个坐标位置了
of the last established position of the shuttlecraft.
- 谢谢 - 稳定，史考特先生
- Thank you, lieutenant. - Steady. No. Mr. Scott.
方位310坐标35已扫描未发现反物质残余
Bearing 3-10 mark 3-5 just cleared. No antimatter residue.
所有扫描器，执行球状搜索程序，最大范围
All scanners, spherical sweep. Range, maximum.
一定要找到他们！
They'll have to pick it up.
要是太空梭本身已经失去动力
If the shuttlecraft powered away, Mr. Scott.
单单靠惯性滑行怎么办？
But if it were just towed?
即使是那样也会有蛛丝马迹的
There'd still be traces of residual matter floating around, lieutenant.
方位210坐标40发现高浓度粒子聚集
Bearing 2-10 mark 4-0. Strong particle concentration.
史考特先生，看来我们这回找对了
We're on it, Mr. Scott.
开始设置追踪航道，继续扫描
Lay on the course. Maintain scanning.
航道已设置
Course laid in, sir.
粒子密度开始衰减了
Particle density decreasing.
完全消散了
Gone, sir. No readings.
苏鲁先生，保持航道
Steady as she goes, Mr. Sulu.
史考特先生，这意味着什么？
What do you think it means, Mr. Scott?
可以推知：至少五小时之前太空梭
The shuttlecraft was on schedule
一直保持在既定航道上
until it was shy five hours of rendezvous.
然后出现了突发情况
Then something happened.
能不能再说得确定一些？
I'd feel a lot better if it were a little more definite.
没有任何碎片残骸，所以太空梭至少不是被摧毁的
It didn't wreck. There was no debris.
没有发现氧气聚集现象，没有残余的放射性
There's no trace of expelled internal atmosphere. No residual radioactivity.
有可能是
It's...
被某个物体掳走了可能，是牵引光束一类的东西
Something took over. Tractor beams, maybe. Something.
那个什么东西就在这个地方把太空梭拖走了
It dragged it away on the heading we're now on.
现在没有任何痕迹了，我们怎样搜寻他们呢？
But if there are no further traces, how are we going to follow them?
我们就保持现在的航道，静观其变吧
We stay on this course. See what comes up.
可是银河系太大了，史考特先生
It's a big galaxy, Mr. Scott.
说得不错
Aye.
这个设备的工作原理是什么？
What's the theory behind this device?
所有的智慧生物的思维模式都是大同小异的
There are certain universal ideas and concepts common to all intelligent life.
这台设备能够匹配讲话者的脑波频率
This device instantaneously compares the frequency of brainwave patterns,
然后辨识出这些频率分别代表的含义
selects those ideas and concepts it recognises,
然后再用特定的语法将其组织起来
and then provides the necessary grammar.
如此一来就能把任何其他语言翻译成英语
Then it simply translates its findings into English.
你的意思是这东西能讲话？
You mean, it speaks?
它可以发出声音或者
With a voice or the approximation
用跟对方相似的方式交流
of whatever the creature is on the sending end.
当然不是百分之百管用，不过凡事没有完美
Not 100 percent efficient, of course, but nothing ever is.
- 史波克先生，可以了吗？ - 可以了，舰长
- Ready, Mr. Spock? - Quite ready, captain.
寇可兰先生
Mr. Cochrane...
把伴随者召唤出来吧
...call the Companion.
伴随者
Companion...
我们想跟你谈谈
...we wish to talk to you.
你们能和我沟通？难道你们能够
How can we communicate? My thoughts...
看见我的思维？
... you are hearing them?
很有趣
This is interesting.
- 史波克，毫无疑问她是雌性 - 是的
- Feminine. No doubt about it, Spock. - Yes.
这个生物体的性别对形势有关键影响
The matter of gender could change the entire situation.
你怎么看？
Way ahead of you.
- 她的角色并非动物管理员 - 不是吗？
- It is not a zookeeper. - No?
更像是一个爱人
A lover.
伴随者
Companion...
违背我们的意愿而把我们囚禁在这里是不对的
...it is wrong to keep us here against our will.
这个男人需要他自己的同类来陪伴他
The Man needs the company of his own kind,
否则他就会消亡
or he will cease to exist.
他就是这样告诉我的
He felt it to me.
如果你不放我们走
One of us will cease to exist
我们中的一个就会马上消亡
if we don't get her to a place where we can care for her.
这个男人需要他的同类作伴
The Man needs others of his species.
这就是你们在此的原因
That is why you are here.
这个男人的生命必须得到延续
The Man must continue.
伴随者，你换位思考一下
Companion, try to understand.
我们的种族天性就向往自由
It is the nature of our species
就好比你的天性就是喜欢待在这里
to be free, just as it is your nature to stay here.
如果我们被囚禁的话，我们会逐渐消亡的
We will cease to exist in captivity.
你们身体的自然老化程序已经被中止了
Your bodies have stopped their peculiar degeneration.
你们没什么好怕的
There will be nothing to harm you.
你们会永恒存在，那个男人亦然
You will continue, and the Man will continue.
这样很合理
This is necessary.
这是拓展我们知识的千载难逢的好机会
This is a marvellous opportunity to add to our knowledge.
你可以询问关于她的生理状态，她种族的历史
Ask it about its nature, its history.
这里不是课堂
This isn't a classroom.
现在首要任务是离开此处
I'm trying to get us out of here.
以后可能没这种机会了
A chance like this may never come again.
这是我们获取新知的绝好机会
It could tell us so much.
现在不是干这个的时候
This isn't the time.
伴随者
Companion...
你提供给我们的根本不是永恒
...what you offer us is not continuation,
而是停滞
it is nonexistence.
如此下去我们会消亡的
We will cease to exist.
那个男人同样也会消亡的
Even the Man will cease to exist.
你们的行为不合逻辑
Your impulses are illogical.
这次交流纯属浪费时间
This communication is useless.
那个男人必须保持存在
The Man must continue.
由此，你们亦可保持存在
Therefore, you will continue.
这是必要的
It is necessary.
舰长
Captain...
你们干嘛把翻译器的音频输出设定为女性的声音？
...why did you build that translator with a feminine voice?
- 我们没 - 但是我明明听见
- We didn't. - But I heard...
寇可兰先生，雄性和雌性是一种普遍区分
The idea of male and female are universal constants, Cochrane.
伴随者的性别无疑是女性
There's no doubt about it, the Companion is female.
- 我不明白 - 你不明白？
- I don't understand. - You don't?
瞎子都能看得出来
A blind man could see it with a cane.
你并非宠物，也不是笼子里的标本
You're not a pet. You're not a specimen kept in a cage.
- 你是她的配偶 - 我是什么？
- You're a lover. - I'm a what?
她对待你的态度和她对待我们的
Her attitude when she approaches you
态度是绝对不同的
is profoundly different than when she contacts us.
当她与你沟通时，态度温柔，优雅
Her appearance is soft, gentle,
她的声音有旋律，愉悦
her voice is melodic, pleasing.
我虽然缺体验情绪的经验
I do not totally understand the emotion
但是我能确定这些不同是存在的
but it obviously exists.
伴随者爱你
The Companion loves you.
你在胡说什么呀？
Do you know what you're saying?
这么些年来，某些非常怪异的感觉在我体内游移不去
For all these years I've let something as alien as that crawl around inside me,
- 我无法摆脱，听凭其行 - 这一点上你无权抱怨
- into my mind, my feelings. - What are you complaining about?
- 毕竟是她让你活下来的 - 那玩意饲养我，消遣我
- It kept you alive, didn't it? - That thing fed on me, used me.
- 我觉得这样很恶心 - 根本没什么值得恶心的
- It's disgusting. - There's nothing disgusting about it.
它只不过是不同于我们的一种生命体而已
It's just another life form, that's all.
你的思维被旧观念限定了
You get used to those things.
我没法赞同你！
You're as bad as it is.
你目前的这种夸张的情绪反应很不符合逻辑
Your highly emotional reaction is most illogical.
你和伴随者的这种关系已经维持了150年
Your relationship with the Companion has for 150 years
从这种关系中可以发掘出情绪上的满足，实用
been emotionally satisfying, eminently practical,
而且完全没有副作用
and totally harmless.
我要说这种关系 是非常符合你的个人利益的
It may indeed have been quite beneficial.
原来未来一切以利益为先？
Is this what the future holds?
人们完全无视尊严和道德？
Men who have no notion of decency or morality?
也许我已经落伍了150年
Maybe I'm 150 years out of style,
但是我绝对不会当外星怪胎的宠物！
but I'm not going to be fodder for any inhuman monster.
很有趣非常狭隘的观念
Fascinating. A totally parochial attitude.
医生
Doctor.
- 我在，哈特福德女士 - 我刚刚听到他说的了
- Right here, Miss Hedford. - I heard him.
他被那个生命体所爱
He was loved...
但是他却对这种爱全然厌恶
...and he resents it.
你做梦了
You just rest.
没有
No.
我不想死
I don't want to die.
我事业有成
I've been good at my job.
但是
But...
我从来没有被爱过
...l've never been loved.
一次也没有
Never.
你知道那是怎样的日子吗？
What kind of life is that?
你知道从来没有被爱过是什么感觉吗？
Not to be loved?
甚至对别人
Never...
示爱
...to have shown love.
他唯一做的就是逃跑
And he runs away from love.
星舰日志，星历3220.3.
Ship's log, stardate 3220.3.
史考特少校
Lieutenant Commander Scott reporting
代替舰长和大副进行记录
in lieu of the captain and the first officer.
我们仍旧在搜索失踪的太空梭
We are continuing our search for the missing shuttlecraft.
长官，接近了一个小行星带
Approaching what seems to be an asteroid belt, sir.
扫描器显示大约有7000个小行星体
Scanners report approximately 7,000 bodies
- 其体积大致分布于A型至M型 - 大气读数呢?
- of sizes running from types A to M. - Atmosphere count?
大约有百分之三十四的小行星体
Approximately 34 percent of the bodies
含有从H型至M型的大气
have atmosphere in types H to M.
很好，现在我们就用最笨的办法搜索
All right then. We do it the hard way.
所有感应器设置为扫描生命体，自动筛选
All sensors set for life-form registration. Automatic selection.
史考特先生，如果说他们就在其中一颗小行星上
Mr. Scott, there are thousands of them out there they could be on,
那我们的搜索范围可是上千颗小行星呀！
if they're on any of them at all.
你说得对，中尉，上千颗
That's right, lieutenant. Thousands.
现在我们只能一颗一颗地找
And we'll look them over, one by one.
伴随者，你爱那个男人吗？
Companion, do you love the Man?
我不知道
I... do not understand.
他对你很重要吗？
Is he important to you?
他对于你来说是不是比任何东西都重要？
More important than anything. Is he?
就好像他是你身体的一部分似的
As though he were a part of you?
他就是我的一部分
He is part of me.
那个男人必须要持续下去
The Man must continue.
他不会持续存在下去的，他会逐渐消亡的
He will not continue. He will cease to exist.
虽然从你的角度看是为了他好
By your feeling for him,
但是你所谓的这种善意却让他感觉窒息
you're condemning him to an existence he will find unbearable.
他会逐渐消亡的
He will cease to exist.
可是他从此不老不死
He does not age. He remains forever.
不老不死的只是他的肉体而已
You speak of his body.
我强调的是他的灵魂
I speak of his spirit.
伴随者，就在那间小房子里
Companion, inside the shelter,
一个女性已经病入膏肓了
a female of our species is dying.
按你的话说，她马上就要停止持续了
She will not continue.
如果你不放我们走，我们都会停止持续的
That is what will happen to the Man unless you release all of us.
我无法理解你的意思
I do not understand.
我们的种族，只有在不断地
Our species can only survive...
征服各种困难中才能使灵魂延续
...if we have obstacles to overcome.
而你直接把所有的困难都清除了
You take away all obstacles.
如果没有困难，我们就没办法使自己变强
Without them to strengthen us,
我们的生命由此会最终枯竭
we will weaken and die.
你只不过是把那个男人当成玩物而已
You regard the Man only as a toy. You amuse yourself with him.
大错特错
You are wrong.
那个男人是整个宇宙中最重要的东西
The Man is the centre of all things.
我珍视他
I care for him.
但是你并没有爱的能力
But you can't really love him.
你对人类的爱情没有丝毫的了解
You haven't the slightest knowledge of love,
爱情是同类之间才会有的一种关系
the total union of two people.
而你是伴随者，而他是人类！
You are the Companion. He is the Man.
你们是完全不同的两个物种
You are two different things.
你们之间没办法真正的交合
You can't join.
你也不懂什么是真正的爱
You can't love.
你虽然能把他的肉体永远困囚于此
You may keep him here forever...
但是实际上，你们的灵魂之间
...but you will always be separate...
却永远隔绝
...apart from him.
如果我是人类的话
If I were human...
是否就可以懂得爱了？
... there can be love?
吉姆，你刚刚说的那番话是为了什么？
What did you hope to gain by that, Jim?
我想劝说她放弃
Try to convince her of the hopelessness of it.
有些时候，爱就意味着放手
Love sometimes expresses itself in sacrifice.
我以为能让她明白真爱要学会放手
I thought maybe if she loved him, she'd let him go.
但是她，或说它，并不是人类
But she, or it, is inhuman, captain.
你不能指望她像人类那样去做
You cannot expect her to react like a human.
- 我试过了 - 没用的
- I tried. - It's useless.
我知道
I know.
杰佛瑞·寇可兰
Zefram Cochrane.
老骨头？
Bones?
我也不清楚是怎么回事，她的病痊愈了
I don't understand it. She's not sick at all.
我们明白
We understand.
是她
It's her.
什么？
What?
你不明白吗？伴随者附体了
Don't you understand? It's the Companion.
老骨头？
Bones?
她现在完全健康，一切生命体征都正常
She's perfectly healthy. Heart like a hammer.
呼吸正常，血压正常
Respiration, normal. Blood pressure, normal.
这在医学上是不可能的
This is medically impossible.
- 我们就是证据 - 你说我们？
- We are here. - We?
是的，我们
Both of us.
我们是协调员和伴随者
Those you knew as the commissioner and the Companion.
我们合成了一个意识
We are both here.
伴随者，你应该没有创造生命的能力
Companion, you do not have the power to create life.
那是上帝的领域
That is for the maker of all things.
但是哈特福德女士已经奄奄一息了
But Commissioner Hedford was dying.
我的意识中哈特福德那部分已经十分虚弱了
That part of us was too weak to hold on.
在某一刻，她几乎要停止延续
In a moment, there would have been no continuing.
不过现在我们在一起了
Now we're together.
那么你和伴随者共处在一个躯体里？
Then you are both here in the one body?
我们合二为一
We are one.
杰佛瑞
Zefram.
我们吓到你了吗？你过去从来不怕我们啊
We frighten you. We've never frightened you before.
孤独
Loneliness.
这种感觉是孤独吗？
This is loneliness.
天那，多么痛苦
Oh, what a bitter thing.
哦，杰佛瑞，太不幸了这些年 你是如何承受这种孤独感的？
Oh, Zefram, it's so sad. How do you bear it, this loneliness?
史波克，检查一下太空梭，引擎，通讯什么的
Spock, check out the shuttlecraft. Engine, communications, everything.
舰长，没有必要
That will not be necessary, captain.
你们的太空梭已经能够正常运作了
Your vehicle will operate as before.
包括通讯系统
So will the communications device.
你同意让我们走了？
You're letting us go?
事到如今我们也无法阻止你们了
We could do nothing now to stop you.
你曾经说过，因为我们不是人类
You said we would not know love
所以我们无法真正第理解人类的爱情
because we were not human.
现在我们是人类了
Now we are human.
我们理解了世间的沧桑变化
We'll know the change of the days.
我们也理解了死亡
We will know death.
但是当我拉住那男人的手
But to touch the hand of the Man
我依旧觉得，没有什么比他更重要
nothing is as important.
你长得非常美丽
You're very beautiful.
我的部分人格明白你说的话，部分却不能
Part of me understands. Part does not.
- 但是我就是爱听 - 我可以详细为你解释
- But it pleases me. - I could explain. Many things.
哦，杰佛瑞，我们一起去散步吧
Oh, let me walk, Zefram.
让我体验一下土地轻触双脚的感觉
Let me feel the earth against my feet.
让我体验一下阳光洒在面颊的温暖
Let me feel the warmth of the sun on my face.
你陪在我身边，我们一起去体验这些美好的东西
You beside me. Let me feel these things.
去吧，寇可兰，我们这边还有事要忙
Go ahead, Cochrane. We have a few things to do.
史考特先生，接收到舰长的信号了
Mr. Scott, it's the captain.
接通
Put him on.
锁定他的坐标
Lock onto his coordinates.
舰长，我是史考特，你们没事吧？
Captain, this is Scotty. Are you all right?
我们没事，你们能锁定我们吗？
Perfectly all right. Can you get a fix on us?
舵手正在计算你们所处的位置
The helm is computing your position now, captain.
方位224，坐标12
Course 2-24 mark 1-2.
地球标准时，57分钟
ETA, 57 minutes.
我们大约于57分钟之后可到达你们的位置
We'll be there in 57 minutes, sir.
很好，我会一直保持通讯畅通
Very good. I'll continue transmitting.
一旦到达指定位置马上进入标准轨道
Assume standard orbit when you arrive.
我们会乘坐太空梭回舰
We'll transport up in the shuttlecraft.
舰长，你们到底发生了什么事？
What happened, captain?
说来话长，史考特先生
Interesting story, Scotty.
我一时和你说不清楚，况且，说老实话
I can't tell you now, because, quite frankly,
我们不知道结局会如何，寇克完毕
I don't know how it's going to end. Kirk out.
外面的任何一件事都会让你大开眼界
Everything will be an eye-opener to you.
有上千颗有生命的星球，上千个种族
There's 1,000 planets out there, 1,000 races.
我们到了外面的世界后，一旦我学习得 差不多了，我也会向你逐一展示
And I'll show everything to you as soon as I learn my way around again.
或许我还可以做些事，来回馈你这些年为我做的一切
Maybe I can make up a little for everything you've done for me.
杰佛瑞，我不能和你一起走
I can't go with you, Zefram.
你当然能跟我走，而且你必须跟我一起
Of course you can. You have to.
我的生命起源于此处
My life emanates from this place.
只要我离开这里，我就会停止延续的
If I should leave it for more than a tiny march of days, I'll cease to exist.
我必须要回来，就如同你们必须要消耗 物质来维持生命
I must return, even as you must consume matter to maintain your life.
你的意思是说如果你要成为人类 就意味着失去你原有的一切？
You mean you gave up everything to be human?
但是，即使你留在这里，你最终还是会死的
But even if you stay here, you'll eventually die.
起码此时此刻
The joy of this hour...
我很快乐
I am pleased.
我不能把你扔在这里自己走
Well, I can't just fly away and leave you here.
杰佛瑞寇可兰，你一定要得到自由
You must be free, Zefram Cochrane.
是你救了我的命
You saved my life.
你照料我，而且还爱我
You took care of me...
我却从来没有理解你的爱
...and you loved me. I never understood.
可是我现在全都明白了
I do now.
我们已经进入标准轨道并且锁定了你们的位置
We're locked in, captain. Standard orbit established.
太空梭停泊港随时准备接收你们
Shuttlecraft Bay standing by to receive you.
史考特，待命
Stand by, Scotty.
寇可兰先生，进取号就在轨道上等我们上去
The Enterprise is waiting, Mr. Cochrane.
恐怕我不能带她走了，一旦她离开这里就会死的
I can't take her away from here. If I do, she'll die.
如果我抛下她，她也会死于孤独
If I leave her, she'll die of loneliness.
我此生已经亏欠她太多
I owe everything to her.
我不能就这么抛下她自己走，我爱她
I can't leave her. I love her.
我这么说吓到你们了吗？
Is that surprising?
从一个地球人嘴里说出这话，我一点不惊异
Not coming from a human being.
毕竟你们原本就是不理性的种族
You are, after all, essentially irrational.
想想吧，寇可兰先生
Think it over, Mr. Cochrane.
外面整个银河系都以你为荣
There's a whole galaxy out there waiting to honour you.
我有她就足够了
I have honours enough.
但是你们两个即使在这里也会继续衰老的
But you will age, both of you.
你们不会永生不死
There will be no immortality.
你们会逐渐地衰老最后死亡
You'll both grow old here and finally die.
千百年来人们不一直都是这样的吗？
That's been happening to men and women for a long time.
如果是和她一起白头偕老
I've got the feeling it's one of the pleasanter things about being human,
我觉得这也不失为一件乐事
as long as you grow old together.
你拿定主意了吗？
Are you sure?
这里水源充足气候也很适宜
There's plenty of water here.
种植食物没问题
The climate is good for growing things.
我将来还打算种植一些无花果树
I might even try and plant a fig tree.
男人自古以来不就是播种者吗？
A man's entitled to that, isn't he?
我现在说的都是心理话，舰长
It isn't gratitude, captain.
我看着她，触摸她
Now that I see her, touch her...
我知道我爱她
...I know that I love her.
我们在这里会很幸福地生活在一起的
We'll have a lot of years together, and they'll be happy ones.
祝你万事顺利
All the best.
舰长，还有一件事
Captain?
别把我的事情告诉别人
Don't tell them about me.
我会保守秘密的，寇可兰先生
Not a word, Mr. Cochrane.
吉姆
Jim.
埃普西隆卡纳瑞三号星上的战争怎么办？
What about that war on Epsilon Canaris III?
我相信星际联邦会另外找到一位有能力
I'm sure the Federation can find another woman somewhere
阻止战争的女士的
who'll stop that war.
TLF字幕组欢迎你，欢迎有志之士加入
TLF微博http://weibo.com/tlfsubs/
TLF中文字幕站http://tlfsubs.eastgame.org/